<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>topoToraster_3d on Node Dangles</title>
    <link>https://maprantala.com/tags/topotoraster_3d/</link>
    <description>Recent content in topoToraster_3d on Node Dangles</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Sep 2010 13:36:34 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://maprantala.com/tags/topotoraster_3d/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Another TopoToRaster Error</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/2010/09/15/another-topotoraster-error/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Sep 2010 13:36:34 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/2010/09/15/another-topotoraster-error/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;subtitled-why-error-messages-are-good&#34;&gt;Subtitled:  Why error messages are good.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Came up with another error while running TopoToRaster but this time ArcGIS gave an error message that led to a solution.  Turned out all my contour lines had an elevation of 16 which TopoToRaster did not like.  I had intended to increase the elevation and inadvertently set them all to sixteen.  I had saved the previous values before editing so it turned out to be a simple fix and I didn&amp;rsquo;t have to spend a day trying figure out what was wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://maprantala.com/images/2010/09/sixteen.jpg?resize=630%2C225&#34; alt=&#34;Sixteen&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TopoToRaster Error</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/2010/09/13/topotoraster-error/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Sep 2010 20:25:01 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/2010/09/13/topotoraster-error/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In running an automated process, I had a TopoToRaster repeatedly fail on me. The only input theme was a contour theme. The process ran fine when I used the envelope of the contour theme as the output extent but when I changed it to the envelope of a polygon theme, it would bomb. The polygon&amp;rsquo;s envelope was smaller than the contour theme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ArcCatalog would bomb out without presenting any sort of useful message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I determined eventually that If I set the left extent as 435210, the process would work if set the right extent to 446655 or greater but would bomb if I used 446654 or less. If the the left extent was 435209, the right extent had to be 446654 or greater.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The image below shows the contours (with vertexes) and the polygon theme I was using. The two circle graphics show the approximate extent I was clipping to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://maprantala.com/images//2010/09/topotoraster.jpg?resize=453%2C381&#34; alt=&#34;topotoRaster&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I eventually wrote python script to do a series of tests with the intent of determining the pattern of what does and does not work. The unexpected benefit was I actually got some sort of error message back. Turns out it had to do with my lack of vertices–I densified my polylines and it ran fine. Something I should have thought of earlier but it was difficult lacking any feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://maprantala.com/images/2010/09/untitled.jpg?resize=535%2C271&#34; alt=&#34;Options&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
