<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Programming on Node Dangles</title>
    <link>https://maprantala.com/categories/programming/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Programming on Node Dangles</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2013 06:47:36 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://maprantala.com/categories/programming/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Arcpy: Check if a field exists</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/2013/09/23/arcpy-check-if-a-field-exists/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2013 06:47:36 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/2013/09/23/arcpy-check-if-a-field-exists/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was helping a co-worker who needed to check if a field exists in their arcpy script. Since we were located at their computer, I thought I would just do a quick Google search and pull the code off this blog. Seemed logical since I the original purpose was exactly that—to serve as a handy, public place to store code snippets that I use &amp;amp; that others might find handy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, my Google Search on “&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/#q=Node+Dangles+field+Exists&#34;&gt;Node Dangles field Exists&lt;/a&gt;” came up with a &lt;a href=&#34;http://maprantala.com/2011/01/27/checking-to-see-if-a-field-index-exists-using-python/&#34;&gt;9.3 script&lt;/a&gt; to check if field index exists. And I also have a &lt;a href=&#34;http://maprantala.com/2011/02/21/checking-to-see-if-a-field-index-exists-using-arcpy-argis-10-0/&#34;&gt;10.0 version&lt;/a&gt; but did not come up with the field exists snippet. So here it is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i0.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/image2.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quick &amp;#038; Dirty arcpy: Autopan ArcMap using arcpy</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/2012/05/02/quick-#038-dirty-arcpy-autopan-arcmap-using-arcpy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 May 2012 05:19:40 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/2012/05/02/quick-#038-dirty-arcpy-autopan-arcmap-using-arcpy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Question: How do I get ArcMap to automatically pan through an area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in a &lt;a href=&#34;http://maprantala.com/2012/04/30/building-a-loc%E2%80%A6f-bing-imagery/&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I recently had the need to have ArcMap automatically pan through a project area. My first attempt was to print a series of data-driven pages (using a fishnet polygon layer as the index) this but that did not accomplish what I needed so I switched to arcpy, which made the task simple enough. Nothing special or tricky about this code, but just did not find it anywhere else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one thing to note is that I have a 1 second pause between pans–this was to allow image tiles to download. You will need to adjust the delay to meet your needs. &lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.dropbox.com/u/22241283/NodeDangles/20120427_AutoPan.zip&#34;&gt;The toolbox and code can also be downloaded&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building a local, permanent cache of Bing Imagery.</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/2012/04/30/building-a-local-permanent-cache-of-bing-imagery./</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2012 05:28:15 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/2012/04/30/building-a-local-permanent-cache-of-bing-imagery./</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently had an internal request to capture and store the Bing imagery for an area for future use. The user was interested in some specific images that were taken after a fire, making the ground surface-and certain geological features-much more visible. His concern was that in the future this imagery might get replaced with updated imagery taken when the vegetation has grown back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since it is unknown when/how this data might be used by us, we mostly wanted to capture it now &amp;amp; find a way to use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While we initiated the process of finding out what agency the data was available through, we also came up with a quick &amp;amp; dirty way to download the data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since ArcGIS 10 has made the process of loading cached basemap data a trivial process through ArcGIS Online, I have not used it much since taking a &lt;a href=&#34;http://maprantala.com/2010/09/09/arcbrutile/&#34;&gt;quick first look&lt;/a&gt; at it in 2010.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After removing my old, forgotten version and installing the latest, shiniest version of ArcBruTile, I verified it was able to display the imagery we wanted. ArcBruTile can be used to “display maps from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.openstreetmap.org/&#34;&gt;OpenStreetMap&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bing.com/maps/&#34;&gt;Bing&lt;/a&gt;,  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.spatialcloud.com/&#34;&gt;SpatialCloud&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mapquest.com/&#34;&gt;MapQues&lt;/a&gt;t,  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.europa-tech.com/&#34;&gt;Europa Technologies&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vr-theworld.com/&#34;&gt;VR-TheWorld Online&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mapbox.com/&#34;&gt;Mapbox&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stamen.com/&#34;&gt;Stamen Design&lt;/a&gt; and others in ArcGIS Desktop”. The cool thing for me was it builds a local cache in an open format–a bunch of jpeg files in a directory structure. All I had to do was clear the cache, and pan through the area of interest at the desired scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could either spend many long boring hours manually panning, go through the process of renting a chimp to do it for me, or write some code to do it for me. I ended up making a fishnet of the area of interest and wrote a python script to pan through the area (to be posted).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After I had the images, I ended up build a Mosaic Dataset and added the images to it.  The last trick I that I had to figure out–and really I just found in it &lt;a href=&#34;http://forums.arcgis.com/&#34;&gt;ArcForums&lt;/a&gt;–was how to &lt;a href=&#34;http://forums.arcgis.com/threads/50978-Relative-paths-in-mosaic-datasets?p=193579#post193579&#34;&gt;create a mosaic dataset using relative paths&lt;/a&gt;. Can not be done, at least in 10, but by using the “Repair…” option to reset paths, you can make the mosaic dataset portable enough that if the reason you wanted to use relative paths was so you could move the data around or to other machines, you can. Just need to repair the paths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now, until we can actually track down the original data, we at least have a usable, archive of the imagery we wanted to preserve and have a way to access it in the field in a non-connected environment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quick &amp;#038; Dirty arcpy: Batch Splitting Polylines to a Specific Length.</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/2011/05/01/quick-#038-dirty-arcpy-batch-splitting-polylines-to-a-specific-length./</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2011 05:01:50 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/2011/05/01/quick-#038-dirty-arcpy-batch-splitting-polylines-to-a-specific-length./</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For some odd reason, I wanted to split all the arcs in a polyline feature class to a specific length–if a specific feature was longer than the target length, it would become two or more separate polyline records.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.dropbox.com/u/22241283/NodeDangles/20110429_Polyline%20Dicer.zip&#34;&gt;bare-bones script&lt;/a&gt; that copies an existing feature class into a new feature class then processes each record, splitting it into multiple records if the polyline is longer than the user-specified tolerance.  Some cautionary notes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is Quick &amp;amp; Dirty code–minimal error catching or documentation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I basically tested this against one feature class (the one I wanted to split) once I got it to work, I quit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is some rounding error–features may be a tad bit off (a few ten-thousandths of a unit).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I did not test against multi-part features.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The tolerance is the native units of the data–if your data is in meters but you want to split the polylines every mile, enter 1,609.344.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have included both a toolbox file (.tbx) and python script (.py).  After loading the toolbox, you’ll have to change the Source of the script by right-clicking on it, selecting the Source tab, and then navigating to the .py file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the code for the Googlebots, but you are better off &lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.dropbox.com/u/22241283/NodeDangles/20110429_Polyline%20Dicer.zip&#34;&gt;just downloading&lt;/a&gt; it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Walkthrough: Building custom UI elements using add-ins (ArcObjects .NET 10 SDK)</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/2011/02/15/walkthrough-building-custom-ui-elements-using-add-ins-arcobjects-.net-10-sdk/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2011 17:05:55 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/2011/02/15/walkthrough-building-custom-ui-elements-using-add-ins-arcobjects-.net-10-sdk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was working my way through this ESRI &lt;a href=&#34;http://help.arcgis.com/en/sdk/10.0/arcobjects_net/conceptualhelp/index.html#//0001000001ms000000&#34;&gt;Walkthrough: Building custom UI elements using add-ins (ArcObjects .NET 10 SDK)&lt;/a&gt;.  And came across a couple minor errors that I had to correct during the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, while implementing the OnClick() code for ZoomToLayer.vb, Visual Studio gave me a “Name ‘ArcMap’ is not declared.” error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/arcmapnotdeclared.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the walk-through, they mention that the ArcMap method of your class.  For me, however, it appeared under the .My method.  Not sure if this is something specific to my set-up or, as I’m guessing, something that got changed after the first documentation was created and the final libraries published.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i0.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/objectbrowser.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fix is just adding  “My.” to the namespace in this line:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I added the code for AddGraphics.vb, I got 8 errors.  There was essentially two errors, repeated four times.  I took a screen shot after fixing the first error pair:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i2.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/errorlist.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fixes in this case was also to use the complete name space path.  Examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Change this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And change this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, the walk-through is very well done, just a couple minor tweaks.  I am now working my way through modifying an existing solution–one that included seven projects–to see if I can create an ArcGIS 10 Add-In.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ArcBruTile</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/2010/09/09/arcbrutile/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Sep 2010 14:38:46 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/2010/09/09/arcbrutile/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Stumbled across &lt;a href=&#34;http://arcbrutile.codeplex.com/&#34;&gt;ArcBruTile&lt;/a&gt;, an ArcMap application that allows you to display map tile services–such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.openstreetmap.org/&#34;&gt;OpenStreetMap&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://maps.google.com/&#34;&gt;Google Maps&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bing.com/maps/&#34;&gt;Bing&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.spatialcloud.com/&#34;&gt;Spatial Cloud&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.osgeo.org/wiki/Tile_Map_Service_Specification&#34;&gt;Tile Map Service&lt;/a&gt; (TMS)–in your ArcMap documents.   It works pretty well from my preliminary testing of it.   I have found that at times that the graphical tiles are distorted but I am guessing it is because they are optimized for display in a specific projection, at specific scales and, in ArcMap, you can use any projection/scale combination you want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a free, open-source project that is still in Beta but definitely an application I plan to keep an eye on.  As with any open-source project, the cool thing is the code is available for you to look at, learn from, and hopefully contribute to.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Icon Transparency</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/2010/09/08/icon-transparency/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Sep 2010 15:47:36 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/2010/09/08/icon-transparency/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Maybe I am just dense, but skimming &lt;a href=&#34;https://c.na1.visual.force.com/apex/ideaView?id=0873000000088YVAAY&#34;&gt;ArcIdeas&lt;/a&gt;, I found out that the transparency for an icon is determined by the upper-left pixel.  Don’t know if this is an ESRI convention or not but thought I would pass it one.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
