<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Running Maps on Node Dangles</title>
    <link>https://maprantala.com/tags/running-maps/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Running Maps on Node Dangles</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2014 05:55:13 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://maprantala.com/tags/running-maps/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday Fave: Tapiriik</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/2014/04/25/friday-fave-tapiriik/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2014 05:55:13 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/2014/04/25/friday-fave-tapiriik/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This &lt;a href=&#34;https://maprantala.com/category/fun-maps/friday-fave/&#34;&gt;Friday Fave&lt;/a&gt; is a little bit different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My interest in geospatial technologies (although we just called it GIS back then) largely because I wanted to measure my running routes more accurately and efficiently than the paper map &amp;amp; scrap of paper method I was using in the early 90s. When I was introduced to GIS, I knew what I was going to use it for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that GPS technology is ubiquitous–I&amp;rsquo;m currently using four different GPS devices, at the same time, on my bike rides–I seldom have to use a map to measure my routes. I may still use &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;MapMyRun.com&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; to plan a route ahead of time if I&amp;rsquo;m running in a new area or trying to plan a loop of a certain distance but GPS has really made it so simple to just go out and run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there are several GPS options available, I have used Garmin ever since their 405 Forerunner came out. This was their first watch that didn&amp;rsquo;t get confused for a Timex-Sinclair 1000 strapped to your wrist.&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i2.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/Zx81-timex-manipulated2.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Timex Sinclair 1000&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Garmin&amp;rsquo;s watches upload their data to &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Gamin Connect,&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; which works fine, but for a project I recently started, I wanted to down load all my data which Garmin Connect does not make easy. I had over 1,000 data logs and downloading them individually was not going to happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A little Googling led me to &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;tapiriik.com&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;, which allows you to share data amongst several different online services that endurance athletes might use including Runkeeper, Strava, Garmin Connect, SportTracks, DropBox.com, and Training Peaks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/Screen-Shot-2014-04-24-at-9.52.48-PM.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can use Tapiriik for free (you just need to visit their website to start synchronization) or for $2 per year they will automatically synchronize data between your accounts. You just provide your account information for whichever sites you want to synchronize and either visit their site or pay $2 and it will automatically share data between your accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I linked to my Garmin Connect and Dropbox accounts and tapiriik and after some chugging, I had .GPX files for all of my data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was easy and didn&amp;rsquo;t take very long. Definitely met my needs–I haven&amp;rsquo;t shared data between other services but I do use the desktop version of SportTracks and considered using their web version of the software but didn&amp;rsquo;t know how I would upload all my data.  Now I know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This product definitely saved me a bunch of time. The one thing I wonder, though, is what does &amp;lsquo;Tapiriik&amp;rsquo; means?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday Fave: Public Workout Maps</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/2014/04/05/friday-fave-public-workout-maps/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2014 05:15:31 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/2014/04/05/friday-fave-public-workout-maps/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When I first found out about GIS, the first application that came to mind was using it to map my running routes. At that time, I was using paper maps and scraps of paper to measure how far I was running each day. GIS obviously offered a better method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost twenty years later, GPS has become so common place that I think we have four or five devices in our household that have GPS capabilities and measuring my runs has become ridiculously simple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that background, you can understand why I love projects like &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;this project&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; by Nikita Barsukov, who compiled publicly available data from &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Endomondo&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; and created maps of public running workout tracks for a variety of European Cities, including this sample from Helsinki.&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i0.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/helsinki.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Barsukov.Net&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flowing Data, using a similar concept, generated &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;similar maps&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; for several cities in the United States, including &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Minneapolis&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;–some areas I know.&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://flowingdata.com/2014/02/05/where-people-run/&#34;&gt;http://flowingdata.com/2014/02/05/where-people-run/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve got about six years of running data of my own that I should use to generate a personal running route map but would be a fun project.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
