<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>XML on Node Dangles</title>
    <link>https://maprantala.com/tags/xml/</link>
    <description>Recent content in XML on Node Dangles</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2011 18:26:53 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://maprantala.com/tags/xml/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Using ArcGIS 9.3.1 Desktop to Extract Data From an ArcGIS 10 Server Geodata Service</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/2011/02/04/using-arcgis-9.3.1-desktop-to-extract-data-from-an-arcgis-10-server-geodata-service/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2011 18:26:53 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/2011/02/04/using-arcgis-9.3.1-desktop-to-extract-data-from-an-arcgis-10-server-geodata-service/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In building our Enterprise GIS Database, we need to support users with different needs.  Some of our users just need to see the data on a map while others may want to download a copy of the data so they can use it within their own desktop system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After doing some exploring, one of the options that looks like it will feel the bulk of our internal needs is to create a &lt;a href=&#34;http://webhelp.esri.com/arcgisdesktop/9.3/index.cfm?TopicName=Types_of_services_in_ArcGIS_Server&amp;amp;anchor=ArcGIS%20Map%20service&#34;&gt;Map Service&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href=&#34;http://webhelp.esri.com/arcgisdesktop/9.3/index.cfm?TopicName=Types_of_services_in_ArcGIS_Server&amp;amp;anchor=ArcGIS%20Geodata%20service&#34;&gt;Geodata Servic&lt;/a&gt;e pair–by creating a Map Service, we can make an easy-to-use visual representation of our data.  Combining that with a paired Geodata Service–a Geodata Service with the same name as the Map Service–we can accommodate those users who want to extract the data to their hard drive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A user who has added paired Map &amp;amp; Geodata Services to an ArcMap dataframe can use the Distributed Geodatabase Toolbar to extract data to a local geodatabase.  The Extract Data button is on the far right of the Distributed Geodatabase Toolbar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://maprantala.com/images/2011/02/distributedgeodatabasetoolbar.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Distributed Geodatabase Toolbar&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, my first attempts at testing this did not work.  It would look like it was processing, I would end up with a .mdb or .gdb file on my hard drive but I could not open it.  I would get a &amp;lsquo;Failed to connect to database. This release of the GeoDatabase is eitehr invalid or out of date. [Unknown GeoDatabase release.]  The Microsoft Jet database engine cannot find the input table or query ‘GDB_ReleaseInfo&amp;rsquo;. Make sure it exists and that its name is spelled correctly.&#39; error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://maprantala.com/images/2011/02/versionerror.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Version Error&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When exporting to an .mdb file, I could open it in Access and see the data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily the error is fairly helpful–I was getting an ArcGIS &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.esri.com/Dev/blogs/geodatabase/archive/2010/03/15/The-Simplified-Geodatabase-Schema-in-ArcGIS-10.aspx&#34;&gt;10 Geodatabase&lt;/a&gt; even though I am running ArcGIS 9.3.1 on my desktop.  I was able to open the exported geodatabases using a copy of ArcGIS 10 on another machine.   The reason for the inconsistency is pretty interesting.  Our office is, and for the foreseeable future, running in a mixed-version environment.  We have a mixture of 9.3.1 and 10 desktops, a 9.3.1 ArcSDE server and a 10 ArcGIS Server.  The Extract Tool is a server-side function apparently that creates a version 10 Geodatabase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way to get around this is to extract the data to XML and then import the XML workspace into a geodatabase.  Not sure if that will work for all schemas but it was successful for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://maprantala.com/images/2011/02/exportxml.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Export XML&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;geo-post-304&#34; class=&#34;geo geo-post&#34; style=&#34;display: none&#34;&gt;
  &lt;span class=&#34;latitude&#34;&gt;44.852994&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;longitude&#34;&gt;-93.55073&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
