<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Model Builder on Node Dangles</title>
    <link>https://maprantala.com/categories/model-builder/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Model Builder on Node Dangles</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2010 14:56:43 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://maprantala.com/categories/model-builder/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Launching a Python script with parameters–3 methods.</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/2010/12/13/launching-a-python-script-with-parameters3-methods./</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2010 14:56:43 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/2010/12/13/launching-a-python-script-with-parameters3-methods./</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Since I use python for different tasks, I launch python scripts a variety of ways. Depending on what I am doing, a single script may need to accept parameters from either:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Passed in from an ArcGIS Toolbox Tool.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Re-occurring default value.  Often used in scheduled processes, a nightly backup, for example.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A temporary set of values used in an interactive, debugging session.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I often do is make the parameter interpretation flexible to meet my needs.  The sample below shows how I do this.  The logic first checks to see if the correct number of parameters were used to launch the script (i.e. if it is called by an Arc Toolbox tool), where the files for the default files exist or if the debug values are valid, including checking the current date against a hard-coded date variable.  Juggling the conditional structure would allow you to prioritize the options differently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am also using Tkinter to display an interactive dialog if none of the three conditions are successfully met.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trying to perform &#39;relate&#39; in Model Builder</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/2010/08/11/trying-to-perform-relate-in-model-builder/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Aug 2010 17:31:21 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/2010/08/11/trying-to-perform-relate-in-model-builder/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was using Model Builder (ugh!) to select records in one table (CWI.C5ST) that relate to a subset of records ([BHGEOPHYS] = ‘Y&#39;) in another table (CWI.C5IX).  There is not an existing tool for doing this in ArcGIS.  I did find a &lt;a href=&#34;http://forums.esri.com/Thread.asp?c=93&amp;amp;f=1728&amp;amp;t=257179&amp;amp;g=1&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; by Layne Seely in &lt;a href=&#34;http://forums.esri.com/&#34;&gt;ArcForums&lt;/a&gt; titled &amp;lsquo;trying to perform &amp;lsquo;relate&amp;rsquo; in Model Builder.&amp;rsquo; that led me to the Make Table View under Data Management Tools-Make Table View and even had  the basic syntax I was looking for (if it hadn&amp;rsquo;t I probably would have guessed that it would not allow subqueries).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I always like to see exactly the syntax someone uses, I decided to show the syntax I used in case that helps anyone else.&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/08/tableview.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Sample of a Table View using a subquery&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It does require that the tables reside in the same workspace, which is a reasonable limitation that I can live with.  Another drawback is that if you export the model to a python script, the command can get pretty long, especially if you have many fields.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
