<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Geology on Node Dangles</title>
    <link>https://maprantala.com/category/geology/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Geology on Node Dangles</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2010 18:15:51 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://maprantala.com/category/geology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>X-section Xacto Updated</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/2010/12/10/x-section-xacto-updated/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2010 18:15:51 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/2010/12/10/x-section-xacto-updated/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I just happened to stumble upon an update of a tool to Create Geologic Cross Sections, eXacto Section v. 2.0, that I &lt;a href=&#34;https://maprantala.com/2010/07/23/create-geologic-cross-sections-exacto-section-v-2-0-arcmap-9-3/&#34;&gt;mentioned&lt;/a&gt; in July. Jennifer Carrell at the Illinois Geological Survey wrote this tool. The latest update is from December 8, 2010 and can be &lt;a href=&#34;http://resources.arcgis.com/gallery/file/geoprocessing/details?entryID=C83CC388-1422-2418-7F10-B4D3DF5F1EE6&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;downloaded at ESRI&amp;rsquo;s ArcGIS Resource Center&lt;/a&gt;. Our office has used previous versions and finds in very useful in creating cross-sections. I have not tried this latest update.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;geo-post-240&#34; class=&#34;geo geo-post&#34; style=&#34;display: none&#34;&gt;
  &lt;span class=&#34;latitude&#34;&gt;44.852994&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;longitude&#34;&gt;-93.55073&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AASG</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/2010/07/09/aasg/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jul 2010 19:49:51 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/2010/07/09/aasg/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was looking for links to all the State Geological Surveys and found the Association of American State Geologists (AASG) &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stategeologists.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Homepage&lt;/a&gt; to have exactly what I needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope to build some sort of inventory of data samples available.  If I do one a day, I can be done in 10 weeks, or about 3 months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I will find the most useful is data distribution methods and data structures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The USGS has a  &lt;a href=&#34;http://maps.ngmdb.us/dataviewer/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;sample web application&lt;/a&gt; and it includes statewide data for four states–Arizona, Idaho, Oregon and Washington, so those, along with Illinois and the states that border Minnesota will be among the first I take a look at.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Geology Information Systems</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/2010/05/24/geology-information-systems/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 May 2010 02:52:24 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/2010/05/24/geology-information-systems/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the last couple months, I&amp;rsquo;ve had a bit of an eye-opening about Geography. People actually trained in geography may implicitly understand this but I, with my Accounting degree, have spent the last 16 years &amp;lsquo;doing&amp;rsquo; GIS without realizing the foundation of geography–geology. I picked up enough geography to understand some of the inter-relationships between people and the lands they live on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what I didn&amp;rsquo;t pick up on was how the lands we live on are formed. Maybe it is a moot point–how physical geography is arrived at doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter, just how we react to it. But, and now working for a Geological Survey, I better have this opinion, a better understanding of what our geology is and how it was formed really does form the foundation for the geography.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two examples. First, in talking with my new supervisor, he was talking about how, because of the geology in the southeast part of the state, they have a lot of water quality issues–the water tends to have sulfur in it. With the recent interest in alternative energy sources, and in this case ethanol plants water quality is a concern when deciding where to build the plants because they require a considerable amount of water. For some reason there have been plants placed in this part of the state and they are having some problems finding sufficient water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second, and I&amp;rsquo;m not sure that this is actually fact or just a theory but it is an interesting idea, was something I read in Malcolm Gladwell&amp;rsquo;s book &lt;em&gt;Outliers&lt;/em&gt;. In the book, it was suggested that there was an almost epidemic of feuds, a la Hatfield-McCoy, in part of the US largely due to the geology of a portion of the country. The areas that relied on a herding economy developed a clannish &amp;lsquo;code of honor&amp;rsquo; that led to these long-term feuds. While I understood that physical geography effects human behavior I hadn&amp;rsquo;t taken the mental step to link geology to physical geography.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pretty silly and probably obvious oversight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And to think, I use to think the &amp;lsquo;G&amp;rsquo; in GIS should really stand for Geometry. Humph!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
