<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>arcpy on Node Dangles</title>
    <link>https://maprantala.com/categories/arcpy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in arcpy on Node Dangles</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 May 2018 17:56:09 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://maprantala.com/categories/arcpy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Using ArcPy.Mapping to update Definition Queries.</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2018-05-08-using-arcpy-mapping-to-update-definition-queries/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 May 2018 17:56:09 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2018-05-08-using-arcpy-mapping-to-update-definition-queries/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Working with a routine process today that I normally only do once in awhile but today needed to do it several times. It requires changing the definition query on several features classes. Being the “lazy” GIS guy that I am (owner of a company I used to work at called me that once as a sort of compliment for my tendency to script a lot of what I did), I decided to finally script it instead of changing definition queries about 42 times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The quick &amp;amp; dirty &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;script&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; code that I wrote &amp;amp; can be run in the ArcMap python window consists of two parts. The first three lines just need to be run once per session to get a variable set with the list of layers. The loop I ran multiple times, updating the “.replace” settings each time. I ran the loop, did my other processes, and re-ran the loop as needed and was a happy GISer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ArcToolbox Tool: Add [ST_CON_ABR] to Hennepin County, MN Centerlines</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2017-10-04-arctoolbox-tool-add-st_con_abr-to-hennepin-county-mn-centerlines/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Oct 2017 22:17:11 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2017-10-04-arctoolbox-tool-add-st_con_abr-to-hennepin-county-mn-centerlines/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the great advancements over the last decade plus in GIS is that government agencies have started to move away from a “recover-our-cost” mentality to more of an “Open Data”. Minnesota, for example, has launched their &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Geospatial Commons&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; as a platform for sharing data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And while getting free, authoritative data is awesome, it can leave you in a bind if the structure of the data changes. Sometime between April and September, Hennepin County, Minnesota, changed the schema of their &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;publicly available street centerlines data&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data used to have both a full, concatenated street name field ([ST_CONCAT]) and an abbreviated version ([ST_CON_ABR]). A record might have “James Lofton Avenue North” and “James Lofton Ave N”, respectively, in these two fields. The abbreviated version was nice for labeling but it disappeared from the most recent updates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/10/Streetnames.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, as you  might guess from the fact that I’m posting about it, I wrote a script to add that field in and launch it from an ArcToolbox Tool. Nothing fancy going on in the code, just a series of replaces, depending on the field. Using dictionaries instead of arrays of paired values might have been better but the script takes just a few seconds to run so I can live with it as-is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The list of street type abbreviations came from a combination of &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;ESRI’s standards&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; and those found in an older version of the Hennepin County data. There were no conflicting abbreviations between the two. The code warns if a street name occurs in the data that is not in the list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I’m including the code here for reference, it’s probably best to &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;download the code from GitHub.&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Converting MXD to Layer file in Arcpy</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2015-08-14-converting-mxd-to-layer-file-in-arcpy/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Aug 2015 10:01:54 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2015-08-14-converting-mxd-to-layer-file-in-arcpy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Working on doing some &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;advanced ArcGIS server printing&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; and had the need to batch convert many existing .mxd files to .lyr files. So instead of opening up X number of map documents, thought I would do it via code. All of my .mxds in this case had just one data frame so the process was pretty simple–I add an empty group layer (Thanks &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Petr Krebs&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; for the idea), copy all the existing layers into it, and save it out as a layer file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I created an ArcGIS toolbox with two options–one to convert a single .mxd and one to batch convert an entire folder. To use it, make sure to have the EmptyGroup.lyr in the same directory as the .py file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the raw code or &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;git it&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Calling os.startfile and webbrowser.open from ArcGIS.</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2014-12-31-calling-os-startfile-and-webbrowser-open-from-arcgis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2014 14:38:16 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2014-12-31-calling-os-startfile-and-webbrowser-open-from-arcgis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I’ve created &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Python add-ins&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; for data entry for our staff. Most of these have a toolbar with a “Help” button that opens a help file in .pdf format.&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i0.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/Toolbar.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Sample python add-in toolbar.&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first add-in was for ArcCatalog and this worked splendidly. I was using os.startfile(&lt;em&gt;path to help.pdf&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, when I started doing ArcMap add-ins, clicking the Help button would open the help.pdf but ArcMap would crash. Oops!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily the &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Python development team at Esri&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; already had a &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;blog post&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; about this at their &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;ArcPy Café blog&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They report that the root of the problem is “conflicts in the way the Windows libraries expect to be called, they can fail or crash when called within ArcGIS for Desktop in an add-in script or geoprocessing script tool”. But this can be overcome by using a &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;decorator&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; function that calls os.startfile from a new thread. Another function effected by these conflicts is webbrowser.open.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Example code is shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then whenever you call startfile or openbrowser, it will be routed through your decorator function and, as far as I’ve been able to tell, works fine without crashing your ArcMap session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cheers!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quick &amp;#038; Dirty Arcpy: Verify a Coded Value Domain Code</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2014-12-18-quick-dirty-arcpy-verify-a-coded-value-domain-code/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2014 22:32:11 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2014-12-18-quick-dirty-arcpy-verify-a-coded-value-domain-code/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been working on a few different data import routines and one of the things I recently built was the ability to verify that a potential Code to be entered into a field with a &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Coded Value Domain&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; is valid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The logic of the code is pretty straight-forward. Get a field’s domain and check that a potential value is one of the code values. The biggest “trick” in this code is that &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;arcpy.da.ListDomains&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;, which locates a field’s domain, takes a geodatabase (or Enterprise geodatabase connection file) as its only parameter. The documentation says it takes a workspace, but it does not like a feature dataset, which a feature class might be in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple caveats about the code. It only returns True if a field exists, has a coded value domain, and the value tested is one of the (case-sensitive) valid codes. While I have an ArcToolbox tool to call it for illustration purposes, I’m only calling it from code so I wanted tight requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, here is the code or &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;download it&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; from GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quick &amp;#038; Dirty ArcPy: Listing Data Sources</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2014-12-03-quick-dirty-arcpy-listing-data-sources/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2014 08:05:10 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2014-12-03-quick-dirty-arcpy-listing-data-sources/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I just had the need to go through a directory containing many (100+) layer files (.lyr) and verify the data sources in each. I could have loaded each into ArcMap and checked the properties, but choose not to. Here’s the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/MapRantala/Blog/blob/master/python/arcpy/20141203_ListDataSources/listDataSources.py&#34;&gt;bare-bones script&lt;/a&gt; I used instead:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quick &amp;#038; Dirty arcpy: Compare Feature Class Table Schemas</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2014-07-07-quick-dirty-arcpy-compare-feature-class-table-schemas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2014 05:06:18 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2014-07-07-quick-dirty-arcpy-compare-feature-class-table-schemas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m in the process of rewriting a process, moving most of the processing from arcpy to postgresql-enabled python (love me some &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;psycopg2&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the QC checks I’m doing at the end of this re-write is just verifying that the feature class schemas are the same (or that the differences are intended)  under the new process as they were in the old process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And while ArcGIS does have a &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;good tool&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; for this, there were a couple tweaks I wanted to make. Most notably, I wanted a list of fields that are not in both feature classes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/TableCompare.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I made a quick &amp;amp; dirty script to do that, nothing especially clever but I’ve found it useful. Download it from &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/MapRantala/Blog/tree/master/ArcToolbox/ArcGIS_10_2/20140702_CompareTableFields&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. I have it currently set up to work on feature layers but you should be able to change the toolbox parameter types to allow feature classes or tables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Zipping a Shapefile from ArcCatalog</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2014-05-06-zipping-a-shapefile-from-arccatalog/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2014 05:42:04 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2014-05-06-zipping-a-shapefile-from-arccatalog/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Back in 2010, I posted a &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;python script &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;and an &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;ArcToolbox&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; tool for zipping a shapefile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I had a request to modify the code so it would not error out if it encounters a .lock file. While .lock files exist for a reason and shouldn’t be totally ignored, in some cases it is safe to do so, so I went ahead any modified the code, which can be downloaded from &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Github&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The guts of the code is here, though:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quick &amp;#038; Dirty arcpy: Bulk Changing Field Values</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2014-04-23-quick-dirty-arcpy-bulk-changing-field-values/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Apr 2014 05:18:24 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2014-04-23-quick-dirty-arcpy-bulk-changing-field-values/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In mapping cross sections, our geologists often find themselves renaming their stratigraphic units midway, or at the end, of creating multiple cross sections.  This can cause a situation where we need to change multiple values in multiple fields in multiple feature classes–a situation that can get messy very fast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perfect situation for a quick &amp;amp; dirty arcpy script and, in this case, an &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/MapRantala/Blog&#34;&gt;ArcToolbox tool that can be downloaded&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This tool will change all feature classes in the O:\clay_cga\sand-distribution_model\dnrPackages\stratlines directory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It will look at two fields, [strat] and [unit] and make these changes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“go” becomes “gro”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“goc” becomes “grc”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“sgb” becomes “grb”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And since I have Case Sensitive checked, “Go” will not get changed to “gro”.  Also note that only full values that match values in the Old Value List get changed, part matches are left as-is so “got” would be left as-is even though the first two characters match “go”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i0.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/BulkFieldChange.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>arcpy.ListFeatureClasses() Bug</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2014-04-02-arcpy-listfeatureclasses-bug/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2014 18:59:06 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2014-04-02-arcpy-listfeatureclasses-bug/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was recently re-evaluating our back-up procedures and discovered and found a nasty bug with the arcpy’s &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;ListFeatureClasses&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; request. If you have a feature class in a feature dataset with the same name, ListFeatureClasses may not find it or anything else in that feature dataset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, we recently made our daily backup a python-based system that uses ListFeatureClasses and got bit by this bug.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After discovering missing data in our backups, I reconstructed what happened and found this bug. Below is arcpy code that iterates through the feature datasets in a geodatabase and lists the feature classes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here is a screen shot of the contents of a test enterprise geodatabase, you’ll see it has a feature data set named “outcrops” that has a feature class also named “outcrops” within it:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/sandbox.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the results list only the feature dataset:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i0.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/results.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if I rename the feature dataset (e.g. outcrop_fd), the results are what I would hope for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i0.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/results.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://i2.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/results2.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found that the feature class does not even need to be within the feature dataset and also the problem does not always occur, I have had the code successfully run in some cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I confirmed the problem, I did find &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;this thread&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; from almost three years ago that mentions the bug. One poster indicated the same thing occurs in ArcObjects which leads me to think something may not be getting registered right in the sde tables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was not able to re-create this using either personal or file geodatabases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I adopting the policy of not using the same name for a feature dataset as for a feature class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Arcpy: Check if a field exists</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2013-09-23-arcpy-check-if-a-field-exists/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2013 06:47:36 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2013-09-23-arcpy-check-if-a-field-exists/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was helping a co-worker who needed to check if a field exists in their arcpy script. Since we were located at their computer, I thought I would just do a quick Google search and pull the code off this blog. Seemed logical since I the original purpose was exactly that—to serve as a handy, public place to store code snippets that I use &amp;amp; that others might find handy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, my Google Search on “&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/#q=Node+Dangles+field+Exists&#34;&gt;Node Dangles field Exists&lt;/a&gt;” came up with a &lt;a href=&#34;http://maprantala.com/2011/01/27/checking-to-see-if-a-field-index-exists-using-python/&#34;&gt;9.3 script&lt;/a&gt; to check if field index exists. And I also have a &lt;a href=&#34;http://maprantala.com/2011/02/21/checking-to-see-if-a-field-index-exists-using-arcpy-argis-10-0/&#34;&gt;10.0 version&lt;/a&gt; but did not come up with the field exists snippet. So here it is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i0.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/image2.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ArcMap Field Calculator: Number of parts in multi-part feature</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2013-09-05-arcmap-field-calculator/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2013 14:04:40 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2013-09-05-arcmap-field-calculator/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the last week, I have looked for multi-part features a couple of times. Today, I was looking for multi-part polygons after dealing with the fall-out of a case of Clip Gone Wild as shown below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i2.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/image.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have not found a way to write a query to find these but Field Calculator does allow you to calculate a field’s value to the number of parts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the Python parser, just write the formula (note that case matters): !shape!.partCount&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i2.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/image1.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SDEINTERCEPT &amp;#038; SDEINTERCEPTLOC</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2012-08-01-sdeintercept-sdeinterceptloc/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2012 07:17:41 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2012-08-01-sdeintercept-sdeinterceptloc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Awhile ago, I had a ArcSDE problem that required &lt;a href=&#34;http://support.esri.com/en/&#34;&gt;ESRI technical support&lt;/a&gt; to help trouble-shoot. The problem was odd but was resolved by rebooting the server.&lt;br&gt;
During the process, though, the support person had me set a couple of environment variables for logging SDE activity on the client machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The settings were SDEINTERCEPT and SDEINTERCEPTLOC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href=&#34;http://help.arcgis.com/en/arcgisdesktop/10.0/help/index.html#//002n00000018000000&#34;&gt;ESRI’s Help&lt;/a&gt;, SDEINTERCEPT specifies what activity to log and SDEINTERCEPTLOC specifies where to save the log files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently deleted the directory I made for the log files but did not remove the variables and I noticed that one of my python scripts reported a weird error (but continued to run, I think). I tracked it back to these variables and realized what I had done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Googling SDEINTERCEPTLOC did lead me to some helpful information like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://sdeintercept.wordpress.com/2011/11/22/sde-user-permissions/&#34;&gt;SDEINTERCEPT blog&lt;/a&gt; where Ken posts ArcSDE help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.esri.com/esri/arcgis/2008/09/05/digging-deeper-troubleshooting-geoprocessing-errors-when-using-arcsde-data/&#34;&gt;ESRI post&lt;/a&gt; about troubleshotting geoprocessing problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this &lt;a href=&#34;http://support.esri.com/en/knowledgebase/techarticles/detail/35704&#34;&gt;ESRI technical&lt;/a&gt; article about diagnosing ArcSDE Connections.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quick &amp;#038; Dirty arcpy: Autopan ArcMap using arcpy</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2012-05-02-quick-dirty-arcpy-autopan-arcmap-using-arcpy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 May 2012 05:19:40 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2012-05-02-quick-dirty-arcpy-autopan-arcmap-using-arcpy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Question: How do I get ArcMap to automatically pan through an area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in a &lt;a href=&#34;http://maprantala.com/2012/04/30/building-a-loc%E2%80%A6f-bing-imagery/&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I recently had the need to have ArcMap automatically pan through a project area. My first attempt was to print a series of data-driven pages (using a fishnet polygon layer as the index) this but that did not accomplish what I needed so I switched to arcpy, which made the task simple enough. Nothing special or tricky about this code, but just did not find it anywhere else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one thing to note is that I have a 1 second pause between pans–this was to allow image tiles to download. You will need to adjust the delay to meet your needs. &lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.dropbox.com/u/22241283/NodeDangles/20120427_AutoPan.zip&#34;&gt;The toolbox and code can also be downloaded&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building a local, permanent cache of Bing Imagery.</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2012-04-30-building-a-local-permanent-cache-of-bing-imagery/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2012 05:28:15 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2012-04-30-building-a-local-permanent-cache-of-bing-imagery/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently had an internal request to capture and store the Bing imagery for an area for future use. The user was interested in some specific images that were taken after a fire, making the ground surface-and certain geological features-much more visible. His concern was that in the future this imagery might get replaced with updated imagery taken when the vegetation has grown back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since it is unknown when/how this data might be used by us, we mostly wanted to capture it now &amp;amp; find a way to use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While we initiated the process of finding out what agency the data was available through, we also came up with a quick &amp;amp; dirty way to download the data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since ArcGIS 10 has made the process of loading cached basemap data a trivial process through ArcGIS Online, I have not used it much since taking a &lt;a href=&#34;http://maprantala.com/2010/09/09/arcbrutile/&#34;&gt;quick first look&lt;/a&gt; at it in 2010.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After removing my old, forgotten version and installing the latest, shiniest version of ArcBruTile, I verified it was able to display the imagery we wanted. ArcBruTile can be used to “display maps from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.openstreetmap.org/&#34;&gt;OpenStreetMap&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bing.com/maps/&#34;&gt;Bing&lt;/a&gt;,  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.spatialcloud.com/&#34;&gt;SpatialCloud&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mapquest.com/&#34;&gt;MapQues&lt;/a&gt;t,  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.europa-tech.com/&#34;&gt;Europa Technologies&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vr-theworld.com/&#34;&gt;VR-TheWorld Online&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mapbox.com/&#34;&gt;Mapbox&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stamen.com/&#34;&gt;Stamen Design&lt;/a&gt; and others in ArcGIS Desktop”. The cool thing for me was it builds a local cache in an open format–a bunch of jpeg files in a directory structure. All I had to do was clear the cache, and pan through the area of interest at the desired scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could either spend many long boring hours manually panning, go through the process of renting a chimp to do it for me, or write some code to do it for me. I ended up making a fishnet of the area of interest and wrote a python script to pan through the area (to be posted).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After I had the images, I ended up build a Mosaic Dataset and added the images to it.  The last trick I that I had to figure out–and really I just found in it &lt;a href=&#34;http://forums.arcgis.com/&#34;&gt;ArcForums&lt;/a&gt;–was how to &lt;a href=&#34;http://forums.arcgis.com/threads/50978-Relative-paths-in-mosaic-datasets?p=193579#post193579&#34;&gt;create a mosaic dataset using relative paths&lt;/a&gt;. Can not be done, at least in 10, but by using the “Repair…” option to reset paths, you can make the mosaic dataset portable enough that if the reason you wanted to use relative paths was so you could move the data around or to other machines, you can. Just need to repair the paths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now, until we can actually track down the original data, we at least have a usable, archive of the imagery we wanted to preserve and have a way to access it in the field in a non-connected environment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ArcMap Field Calculator: Identifying Unique Cases, Single Field</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2012-04-28-arcmap-field-calculator-identifying-unique-cases-single-field/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Apr 2012 05:55:34 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2012-04-28-arcmap-field-calculator-identifying-unique-cases-single-field/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Seems like a lot of people are finding the ArcMap Field Calculator &lt;a href=&#34;http://maprantala.com/category/esri/arcmap-esri/field-calculator/&#34;&gt;examples&lt;/a&gt; that I have posted useful so I will make an effort to post more of them. Most posts are generated after I do something and think that others might want to know how to do it. (Or so I can go back and remember how I did something without re-inventing it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something I did today was create a field (!Case!) and then populated this with a unique identifier for each different value (case) that occurred in a different field (!Feature!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note: python’s &lt;em&gt;index&lt;/em&gt; statement is a 0-based search so the first case will have the value 0, the second will have 1, and so on. If you want to start the results at 1, you can make the last line: “return caseList.index(inValue) + 1”.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic structure for this is shown:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ArcMap Field Calculator: Identifying Unique Cases, Multiple Fields</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2012-04-23-arcmap-field-calculator-identifying-unique-cases-multiple-fields/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Apr 2012 06:06:25 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2012-04-23-arcmap-field-calculator-identifying-unique-cases-multiple-fields/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You may have noticed that this post–&lt;a href=&#34;http://wp.me/pVrsJ-bf&#34;&gt;ArcMap Field Calculator: Identifying Unique Cases, Single Field&lt;/a&gt;–specifies “Single Field”. Yes, that was my version of a cliff-hanger post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic structure I listed in that post can be expanded on to satisfy your needs. The example in my earlier post was case sensitive for example, you could modify it so it treats “a” the same as “A”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today’s example groups records into different cases based off the values of two fields, !county_c! and !feature! and required only minor modifications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The calling line was modified from:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;to accommodate passing both values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The function definition likewise was modified to accept two values, this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this line was added, creating a list from the two values passed in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;**(Note: The same results could have be achieved by using the original function by creating the list in the calling statement:  returnCase([!county_c!,!feature!] )&lt;br&gt;
**&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i2.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/case_multiple.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ArcMap Field Calculator: Text to Double</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2012-03-28-arcmap-field-calculator-text-to-double/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Mar 2012 05:23:32 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2012-03-28-arcmap-field-calculator-text-to-double/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Received a request yesterday asking how to use the ArcMap Calculator to copy values from a Text field to a Double field using python syntax.  As any good blogger would do, I immediately thought, “Awesome! Someone’s question is the perfect topic for a new blog post”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The python parser is actually pretty good at casting values on the fly so if the values in your text field (!Day! in my example) are valid values that can be converted to a Double value, it is as simple as just setting the formula to be the text field. In my example case, I wanted to copy the value from !Day! to !DecDay! so I set the formula to be DecDay = !Day!.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/tonumber1.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That should work fine if you have clean values in your text field. In the example above, you might notice I had a selected set of 3 records that all had numeric values in the !Day! field. When I included the fourth row, which does not have a numeric value in the text field, I get this error message (“There was a failure during processing, check the Geoprocessing Results window for details.” when I use the same formula. Time to add in an error exception.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/tonumber2b.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more advanced logic, the Field Calculator dialog allows you to use a python function if you check on the “Show Codeblock” option.  In the “Pre-Logic Script Code” area (Seriously, who at ESRI came up with that name?) I entered the following function. If the value in my text field (!Day!) can be cast to a number of type float, that value is returned. If the cast is unsuccessful (IE the value in !Day! is not a number), then I return -99.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then in the formula portion of the dialog, I call the function, passing the value in the !Day! field: DecDay = toNum(!Day!).&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/tonumber2.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, if you would prefer not to set all the records with non-numeric values to be -99 or other error value, not return anything. To do this, I replaced the “return -99” in the original function with a filler line (“doNothing = 4”) since the try block needs an non-empty except clause.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i0.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/tonumber3.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
And that should leave the values in the double field unscathed in your records with non-numeric values in the text field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shameless Plug: Check out my other blog posts on using ArcMap’s Field Calculator to &lt;a href=&#34;http://maprantala.com/2011/03/08/calculating-geometry-using-arcpy-in-field-calculator/&#34;&gt;calculate geometry&lt;/a&gt; and converting a date value to an &lt;a href=&#34;http://maprantala.com/2011/10/06/field-calculator-arcpy-date-to-decimal-function/&#34;&gt;8 digit numeric value&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quicker &amp;#038; Cleaner python recursive folder search</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2012-03-14-quicker-cleaner-python-recursive-folder-search/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Mar 2012 17:28:59 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2012-03-14-quicker-cleaner-python-recursive-folder-search/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As contributor of the day, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cleanstick.net/jason/&#34;&gt;Jason Scheirer&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://maprantala.com/2012/03/13/quick-dirty-python-recursive-folder-search-2/#comments&#34;&gt;pointed out&lt;/a&gt;, python has a simple, direct way to browse through the subdirectories of a directory–&lt;a href=&#34;http://docs.python.org/library/os.html#os.walk&#34;&gt;os.walk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a bare-bones example of using it to print out the subdirectories in a path. The files variable of the 3-tuple is a list of files similar to the dirs variable that I loop through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks Jason for pointing out something I missed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i0.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/dirstalker21.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quick &amp;#038; Dirty python recursive folder search</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2012-03-13-quick-dirty-python-recursive-folder-search-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Mar 2012 15:55:55 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2012-03-13-quick-dirty-python-recursive-folder-search-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Someone asked how to have python recursively search a folder structure. There may be a better way but this is how I typically do it–it basically starts with one directory and loops through the contents compiling a list of sub-directories as it goes through the contents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i0.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/dirstalker.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ArcMap Field Calculator: ArcPy Date to Decimal Function</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2011-10-06-field-calculator-arcpy-date-to-decimal-function/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2011 21:08:35 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2011-10-06-field-calculator-arcpy-date-to-decimal-function/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the standards in our databases is to store dates as 8-digit integer values in the format of yyyymmdd. This requires us to occasionally convert values from date fields into this format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can do this in the ArcMap Field Calculator using this arcpy function:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/10/datetodouble.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ArcMap Field Calculator: Create a Unique ID</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2011-07-28-using-arcpy-in-arcgis-10-field-calculater-to-create-a-unique-id/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jul 2011 20:08:13 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2011-07-28-using-arcpy-in-arcgis-10-field-calculater-to-create-a-unique-id/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the common functions I have to do is assign each record in a feature class with a unique identifier–normally just a sequential number from 1 to N.  In ArcView 3.x, the formula was simply “rec + 1” if I wanted to start with the number 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In ArcGIS, the process got a little more complex–you had to write a little VBA in Field Calculator as &lt;a href=&#34;http://support.esri.com/en/knowledgebase/techarticles/detail/27427&#34;&gt;described by ESRI&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this option still exists in ArcGIS 10, I believe it will disappear when 10.1 comes out and VBA support is completely eliminated.  But it is doable using Python which will continue to be supported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Googling around, I did not find an exact answer but Dave Verbyla, Professor of GIS/Remote Sensing at the University of Alaska has a &lt;a href=&#34;http://nrm.salrm.uaf.edu/~dverbyla/nrm638/lectures/Python_field_calculator.pdf&#34;&gt;posted some samples&lt;/a&gt; that served as a good starting point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Pre-Logic Script Code box, I declare a variable (counter) and a function. Then in the formula, I call the function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/07/fc-arcpy.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While composing this post, I actually wanted a concatenated value; “OC” plus an 8 character numeric sequential number starting at OC00000001 so the actual code is shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/07/fc-arcpy2.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Debugging a Python Scheduled Task</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2011-07-11-debugging-a-python-scheduled-task/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2011 18:11:13 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2011-07-11-debugging-a-python-scheduled-task/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been working on a python script that I want (NEED) to run as a scheduled task on a remote machine.  I got to the point that the script did exactly what I needed when I was interactively running it in a Windows session but had problems when running it as a scheduled task.  The debugging process was cumbersome–make a change, schedule a task to run it, log out of the machine, and wait.  The log back in and repeat the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That got old.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I wrote &lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.dropbox.com/u/22241283/NodeDangles/20110711_tester.zip&#34;&gt;a script  (tester.py)&lt;/a&gt; that calls any other python scripts in the same directory that (1) start with “test_” and (2) there is not a corresponding file with the same base name and “.start” extension.  It would launch “test_BaBing.py” as long as there is not a “test_BaBing.start” in the same directory.  Tester.py continued to run, looping every 60 seconds, until tester.stop exists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This made the process easier because I could work on my local machine, editing the problematic script, saving changes and within 60 seconds it would be launched on the remote machine.  I could view the results, make additional edits, delete the .start file and it would launch again within 60 seconds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within a couple minutes I was able to determine the problem (path related) and fix it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy programmer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;I would recommend using this only while debugging a script–routinely running it could be a security risk since someone could copy a destructive python script into the directory and this would run it.&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Download: &lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.dropbox.com/u/22241283/NodeDangles/20110711_tester.zip&#34;&gt;tester.py&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Checking to see if a Field Index Exists Using Arcpy (ArGIS 10.0) redux</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2011-07-05-checking-to-see-if-a-field-index-exists-using-arcpy-argis-10-0-redux/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2011 12:53:34 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2011-07-05-checking-to-see-if-a-field-index-exists-using-arcpy-argis-10-0-redux/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve previously posted python code to check if a field index exists for both &lt;a href=&#34;http://maprantala.com/2011/01/27/checking-to-see-if-a-field-index-exists-using-python/&#34;&gt;ArcGIs 9.3&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://maprantala.com/2011/02/21/checking-to-see-if-a-field-index-exists-using-arcpy-argis-10-0/&#34;&gt;ArcGIS 10.0&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I have been working on a process that was using this code but it was not working because it looks for an index with a specific name.  It was not working in this case because the name of the indexes was getting incremented as they were being created.  For example, I was building an index on the table C5ST, field RelateId ([C5IX].[Relateid]) named I_C5IX_RelateId.  That worked fine until we switched our process so now we keep multiple versions of some tables, each with a date-based suffix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We now have tables name C5St_20110625 and C5St_20110626–the Index-name scheme, however was still creating I_C5IX_RelateId and it worked great on the first one.  But when it created the second one, even on a different table, it was automatically name I_C5IX_RelateId_2 even though the name I_C5IX_RelateId was used when trying to create the index.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before generating relates, our code checks to see if the key fields are indexed, and if they are not, builds  an index.  Because of the naming situation, multiple, duplicate indexes were being created.  Probably not too harmful but it is a little messy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I re-wrote the code so that you pass the function the table name and field name that you want to check and it checks to see if there is an index existing for that field and return a Boolean.  The one little wrinkle I put in is to account for indexes that span multiple fields–the ” if (iIndex.fields[0].Name.upper() == fieldname.upper()):” statement is checking the index to see if it is on a single field or multiple fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;def fieldHasIndex(tablename,fieldname):&lt;br&gt;
if not arcpy.Exists(tablename):&lt;br&gt;
return False&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;tabledescription = arcpy.Describe(tablename)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;for iIndex in tabledescription.indexes:&lt;br&gt;
if (len(iIndex.fields)==1):&lt;br&gt;
if (iIndex.fields[0].Name.upper() == fieldname.upper()):&lt;br&gt;
return True&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;return False&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Feature classes and Tables with names starting with &amp;#8220;nd_&amp;#8221;.</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2011-05-23-feature-classes-and-tables-with-names-starting-with-nd/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2011 15:55:24 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2011-05-23-feature-classes-and-tables-with-names-starting-with-nd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Random luck me to discovering a bug related to feature classes whose names start with “nd_”.  It appears that you are allowed to create feature classes starting with “nd_” but ArcCatalog will not display them.  Further research shows this behavior also occurs for table and for ArcSDE (PostGres) geodatabases,  personal geodatabase, and file geodatabases–I am using ArcCatalog 10.0.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first noticed something odd was occurring while importing a series of shapefiles into a geodatabases.  After importing 15 shapefiles, I only had thirteen feature classes despite receiving no errors during the process.  The two shapefiles that failed to import were named ND_oil_and_gas.shp and ND_Bendix_Study.shp.  Subsequent attempts to import them individually returned an error “Invalid Target Name”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/05/invalidtargetname.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I discovered in pgAdmin III (Postgres SDE Geodatabase) that the table existed and there was an entry in sde.sde_layers for the feature class but ArcCatalog refused to show it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i0.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/05/nd_2.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used some un-supported methods to try to resolve the problem and despite some sweating, I failed to find a way to get ArcCatalog to display these feature classes.  I did, however, at least found a way to delete them–arcpy can detect that the feature classes exists so it is able to delete them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i2.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/05/arcpy_delete.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least by deleting them, I can prevent leaving “invisible” feature classes from hanging out in my geodatabase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suspect the problems stems from how ESRI has implemented the &lt;a href=&#34;http://help.arcgis.com/en/arcgisdesktop/10.0/help/index.html#//002p0000007m000000.htm&#34;&gt;Network dataset table-naming structure&lt;/a&gt; –dirty areas are stored in tables named &lt;em&gt;nd_&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;_dirtyareas _ and &lt;em&gt;nd_&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;_dirtyobjects&lt;/em&gt;.  Possibly the developer  working on the ArcCatalog GUI ended up suppressing showing feature classes and tables whose names start with “nd&lt;/em&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, just for posterity’s sake, here is a python code snippet listing the feature classes in a workspace:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;import arcpy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;arcpy.env.workspace = “c:/temp/_nd/F.gdb”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;print arcpy.env.workspace&lt;br&gt;
for fc in arcpy.ListFeatureClasses():&lt;br&gt;
print fc&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;print “Done!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Renaming Raster Dataset and arcpy.Exists()</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2011-05-03-renaming-raster-dataset-and-arcpy-exists/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2011 09:33:48 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2011-05-03-renaming-raster-dataset-and-arcpy-exists/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Discovered something today. I was working on an arcpy script that copies a raster dataset from a file geodatabase into a Postgres SDE geodatabase and then does some boring routine tasks–building stats, creating a mosaic dataset, adding the raster to the mosaic dataset and making a couple referenced mosaic datasets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It sometimes has trouble with the initial step of uploading the raster because of the sheer size of if (1m elevation raster for counties) and it failed today on one. It failed today so I used the ArcCatalog GUI to copy the raster and renamed it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then proceeded to run launch my script. Before each step, I use &lt;a href=&#34;http://help.arcgis.com/en/arcgisdesktop/10.0/help/index.html#/Exists/000v00000021000000/&#34;&gt;arcpy.Exists&lt;/a&gt;() extensively to check to see if various items exist before I attempt to create them. It was continuously reporting that my raster set did not exist even though I could see it in ArcCatalog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I realized that I needed to close ArcCatalog before arcpy recognized the fact I had renamed something. To note, I was running arcpy from a separate PythonWin window, not from the ArcCatalog session I had renamed the raster dataset with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I closed ArcCatalog, arcpy recognized the renaming and life was good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m also suspicious now about a problem I often have running statistics on my rasters.  The ArcTool reports no errors when I create them but for some reason the raster does not show that it has statistics afterwards.  I normally have multiple ArcApplication sessions open and now suspect that perhaps this problem is due to sessions not letting go of the connection.  Stay tuned for further developments on this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quick &amp;#038; Dirty arcpy: Batch Splitting Polylines to a Specific Length.</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2011-05-01-quick-dirty-arcpy-batch-splitting-polylines-to-a-specific-length/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2011 05:01:50 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2011-05-01-quick-dirty-arcpy-batch-splitting-polylines-to-a-specific-length/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For some odd reason, I wanted to split all the arcs in a polyline feature class to a specific length–if a specific feature was longer than the target length, it would become two or more separate polyline records.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.dropbox.com/u/22241283/NodeDangles/20110429_Polyline%20Dicer.zip&#34;&gt;bare-bones script&lt;/a&gt; that copies an existing feature class into a new feature class then processes each record, splitting it into multiple records if the polyline is longer than the user-specified tolerance.  Some cautionary notes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is Quick &amp;amp; Dirty code–minimal error catching or documentation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I basically tested this against one feature class (the one I wanted to split) once I got it to work, I quit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is some rounding error–features may be a tad bit off (a few ten-thousandths of a unit).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I did not test against multi-part features.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The tolerance is the native units of the data–if your data is in meters but you want to split the polylines every mile, enter 1,609.344.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have included both a toolbox file (.tbx) and python script (.py).  After loading the toolbox, you’ll have to change the Source of the script by right-clicking on it, selecting the Source tab, and then navigating to the .py file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the code for the Googlebots, but you are better off &lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.dropbox.com/u/22241283/NodeDangles/20110429_Polyline%20Dicer.zip&#34;&gt;just downloading&lt;/a&gt; it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Change Detector arcpy Script</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2011-04-08-change-detector-script-arcgis-resource-center/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2011 10:48:59 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2011-04-08-change-detector-script-arcgis-resource-center/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During a process I was working on, I needed to compare a feature class before and after some edits.  I did not quickly find anything in ArcToolbox but searching &lt;a href=&#34;http://resources.arcgis.com/&#34;&gt;ArcResources&lt;/a&gt; led me to &lt;a href=&#34;http://resources.arcgis.com/gallery/file/Geoprocessing-Model-and-Script-Tool-Gallery/details?entryID=351BEE10-1422-2418-8815-82074A3E6B6C&#34;&gt;Change Detector script by Bruce Harold&lt;/a&gt;.  After making a couple of tweaks–for some reason in one of my feature classes, the Shape field had an upper case “S” and in the other it was a lower case “s”.  I also discovered that it needs to export to the same format (personal geodatabase, file geodatabase, shapefile) as the source data (or at least one that uses the same field name deliminator).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After minor adjustments, though, it worked like a charm.  I’ll be submitting the changes I made to Bruce and let him incorporate the changes into the official code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FOLLOW-UP: Mr. Harold quickly responded to my email &amp;amp; made the change (although I haven’t checked it). Way to go Bruce!  Thanks for a handy script.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quick &amp;#038; Dirty arcpy: Field Listings</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2011-03-17-quick-dirty-field-listings-using-arcpy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2011 17:03:39 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2011-03-17-quick-dirty-field-listings-using-arcpy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have to often get a table structure for a feature class or table into either a spreadsheet or word processing document.  There might be an easy way to do this in ArcGIS 10 but I haven’t found it.  So, as is my nature, I decided to roll my own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a &lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.dropbox.com/u/22241283/NodeDangles/20110316_ListFieldCounts-arcpy.zip&#34;&gt;bare-bones script&lt;/a&gt; that iterates through the fields, printing the field name, type, width, and precision.  There are three optional features to it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can choose to have it list the domain, if there is one, on each field.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can have it write to a text file (otherwise you can just copy &amp;amp; paste the results from the results window).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can have it count the number of populated records.  This can take a long time if working with a large dataset.  Also note that my logic for determining what constitutes being populated may not be what you need but the structure is there.  I also do not account for all field types, if the field is of a type I have not account for, the code will return -999.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To use the script from ArcToolbox, you need to pass it four parameters, their Names, type, whether they are input or output, and whether they are required or optional are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;featureclass, Table, Input, Required&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;includedomainstring, Boolean, Input, Required (controls whether or not domains are exported)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;doCountsRespone, Boolean, Input, Required (controls whether or not you want to get the number of populated records.  (Your definition of populated may vary from my code)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;outputFile, File, Output, Optional (optional output file to write)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the code, but you are better off &lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.dropbox.com/u/22241283/NodeDangles/20110316_ListFieldCounts-arcpy.zip&#34;&gt;just downloading&lt;/a&gt; it since I haven’t figured out a good way to have WordPress play nicely with python’s indenting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using arcpy to List Domains Assigned to Featureclass Fields</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2011-03-14-failed-to-delete-domain-from-dataset-the-domain-is-used-as-default-domain/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Mar 2011 18:04:36 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2011-03-14-failed-to-delete-domain-from-dataset-the-domain-is-used-as-default-domain/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was making an edit (adding leading “0”s) to a coded-value domain in an SDE database and realized that my edits were changing the order of the rows of my domain.  Rows were moved to the bottom of the list when they were edited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I went through the process of converting my domain back to a table, made my edits in Access and exported the rows to a .dbf in the order I wanted them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I removed the domain from the field I knew it was assigned to but when I tried to delete the domain, I received an error (The domain is used as a default domain).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/03/failedtodeletedomain.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Google Machine led me to an &lt;a href=&#34;http://forums.esri.com/Thread.asp?c=93&amp;amp;f=985&amp;amp;t=303616&#34;&gt;ArcForums post&lt;/a&gt; by  with some python code for listing all the fields with a domain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tweaked the original a bit, first because it was only examining feature classes in a feature dataset, not stand-alone feature datasets.  And secondly, I updated it to use arcpy.  I posted both the &lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.dropbox.com/u/22241283/NodeDangles/20110314_ListDomains-9_3.zip&#34;&gt;9.3 version&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.dropbox.com/u/22241283/NodeDangles/20110314_ListDomains-10.zip&#34;&gt;10.0 version&lt;/a&gt;, but here is a quick look.  The key addition is the ‘listfc(“”)’ line that is the first line of the def listds() module.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ArcMap Field Calculator: Calculating Geometry using arcpy</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2011-03-08-calculating-geometry-using-arcpy-in-field-calculator/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2011 09:30:40 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2011-03-08-calculating-geometry-using-arcpy-in-field-calculator/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the things I had not gotten around to doing in ArcGIS 10 was figure out how to directly manipulate the geometry of a record using the &lt;a href=&#34;http://help.arcgis.com/en/arcgisdesktop/10.0/help/index.html#//005s00000025000000.htm&#34;&gt;Field Calculator&lt;/a&gt;.  When I stumbled upon a bug in the way the &lt;a href=&#34;http://maprantala.com/2011/03/07/extract-values-to-points-spatial-analyst-bug/&#34;&gt;Extract Values to Points&lt;/a&gt; tool handles Null geometries, I figured it was time to figure it out.  Setting the X, Y to 0,0 was sufficient for my needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I set the Parser to Python and the formula was simple once I figured out the syntax:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i2.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/03/origin.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, to extend my knowledge, I wanted to see how to calculate the geometry based off of two fields (X and Y).   The only real trick is knowing the bracket field names using exclamation points instead of brackets:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i2.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/03/fields.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So turns out everything it pretty easy and straight-forward.  Whew!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Loading Tiled, Same-Name Data in Batch Mode.</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2011-02-28-loading-tiled-same-name-data-in-batch-mode/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2011 12:30:43 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2011-02-28-loading-tiled-same-name-data-in-batch-mode/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been loading existing raster data into a geodatabase to be included in a new Mosaic Dataset–a very cool and useful addition to ArcGIS 10. The most time-consuming part of the process for the human (at least this human) has been getting the names of the rasters right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our existing data is organized by tiles with the directory name representing the tile name and then the data within each tile directory having the same name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;br&gt;
C:\GIS_dataAdamsparcels.shp&lt;br&gt;
C:\GIS_dataBuchetteparcels.shp&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This makes batch loading the data less efficient because I end up having to rename the data or else end up with a series of feature classes named parcels, parcels_2, parcels_n.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I hacked out a quick script that takes an input raster and figures out the final name I want it to have based of the directory name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I used the Copy Raster (In ArcToolbox: Data Management-Raster-Raster Dataset-Copy Raster) and copied on sample to my geodatabase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, I went to the Results Tab (Select Geoprocessing from the Menubar, Geoprocessing-Results) and right-clicked on the Copy Raster result and selected “Copy as Python Snippet”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then created a new python script and pasted the one line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I added some imports, accepted a parameter, some string manipulation, and some result outputs and I had a quick &amp;amp; easy script. In added the script in ArcToolbox and now I can right-click on it and run it in Batch mode. I do a quick search in Windows Explorer to get all the rasters I want to run it on and select &amp;amp; drag them to my ArcToolbox Batch Dialog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actual code can be downloaded &lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.dropbox.com/u/22241283/NodeDangles/20110228_load_lidar_data.zip&#34;&gt;HERE&lt;/a&gt; and you don’t need to worry about WordPress messing up the spacing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Checking to see if a Field Index Exists Using Arcpy (ArGIS 10.0)</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2011-02-21-checking-to-see-if-a-field-index-exists-using-arcpy-argis-10-0/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Feb 2011 09:55:35 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2011-02-21-checking-to-see-if-a-field-index-exists-using-arcpy-argis-10-0/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Updating some python code from 9.3 that using geoprocessing  to 10.0 using arcpy and the first real object I’ve had to change relates to detecting whether or not an index exists on a table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I previously &lt;a href=&#34;http://maprantala.com/2011/01/27/checking-to-see-if-a-field-index-exists-using-python/&#34;&gt;posted code&lt;/a&gt; using a 9.3 geoprocessing commands, the core of it being:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With arcpy, ESRI has gone back to using the &lt;a href=&#34;http://help.arcgis.com/en/arcgisdesktop/10.0/help/index.html#/Describe/000v00000026000000/&#34;&gt;Describe&lt;/a&gt; methodology.  Way back when GISers use to type most of their commands into their wood-burning computers, the command “Describe” was used to retrieve information about a coverage, grid, or other data set in our fancy AMLs (or SMLs).  The snippet below shows a function for checking to see if a table has an index with a specified named.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
