<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ArcObjects on Node Dangles</title>
    <link>https://maprantala.com/categories/arcobjects/</link>
    <description>Recent content in ArcObjects on Node Dangles</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2014 18:59:06 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://maprantala.com/categories/arcobjects/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>arcpy.ListFeatureClasses() Bug</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2014-04-02-arcpy-listfeatureclasses-bug/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2014 18:59:06 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2014-04-02-arcpy-listfeatureclasses-bug/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was recently re-evaluating our back-up procedures and discovered and found a nasty bug with the arcpy’s &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;ListFeatureClasses&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; request. If you have a feature class in a feature dataset with the same name, ListFeatureClasses may not find it or anything else in that feature dataset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, we recently made our daily backup a python-based system that uses ListFeatureClasses and got bit by this bug.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After discovering missing data in our backups, I reconstructed what happened and found this bug. Below is arcpy code that iterates through the feature datasets in a geodatabase and lists the feature classes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here is a screen shot of the contents of a test enterprise geodatabase, you’ll see it has a feature data set named “outcrops” that has a feature class also named “outcrops” within it:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/sandbox.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the results list only the feature dataset:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i0.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/results.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if I rename the feature dataset (e.g. outcrop_fd), the results are what I would hope for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i0.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/results.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://i2.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/results2.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found that the feature class does not even need to be within the feature dataset and also the problem does not always occur, I have had the code successfully run in some cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I confirmed the problem, I did find &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;this thread&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; from almost three years ago that mentions the bug. One poster indicated the same thing occurs in ArcObjects which leads me to think something may not be getting registered right in the sde tables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was not able to re-create this using either personal or file geodatabases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I adopting the policy of not using the same name for a feature dataset as for a feature class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unsupported Arc: &amp;#8220;Rebox&amp;#8221;ing or updating the extent of a feature class.</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2012-06-05-unsupported-arc-reboxing-or-updating-the-extent-of-a-feature-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jun 2012 21:16:28 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2012-06-05-unsupported-arc-reboxing-or-updating-the-extent-of-a-feature-class/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve found that sometimes I can not find the answer to a question until I know the answer &amp;amp; then it becomes ridiculously easy to find the answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One small annoying thing that I never spent much time was when you delete features from a feature class making it significantly smaller but the envelope does not get re-sized so the zoom extent (still the original extent) is too large. This often happens to use when we convert tables to an XY theme and there are blank records–most of our data shows in Minnesota but there are some in Oklahoma (I think). Once we eliminate or correct the blank records, our data view still pops out to include a large section of the United States even though we only have data in Minnesota.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A long, long time ago, &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Workstation ArcInfo&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; had a simple command, &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Rebox&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;, for just this purpose (actually it still does, I just don’t get to use it anymore)–it shrunk the extent to the smallest rectangle required to enclose all the data. Up until today, I thought &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;the request&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; for this feature was completely ignored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While researching something else, I was digging around in the sde tables and found one, sde.sde_layers, that had the interesting fields, minx, miny, maxx, and maxy. My quick &amp;amp; dangerous test (I performed it on a throw-away feature class in a throw-away geodatabase) gave me the results I wanted–once I loaded the feature class into ArcMap, the extent was a nice, tight rectangle around my features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i0.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/06/extent1.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is this a supported way to Rebox the extent? No.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is it recommend by ESRI or me? No.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Will it screw up your entire geodatabase, making you lose all your data &amp;amp; costing you your job? Probably not but do you want to take that chance?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Will it get the job done? Maybe.  But in the process of writing this post, I found two safer ways to go about it. First, the straight-forward, sde command-line way that probably always existed that I never found until today, &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;sdelayer -o alter had an -E option to reset the extent&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;, including the ability to either specify it or have sde calculate it. Ok, that is usable for one person in our organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previously, we had found either a VBA or other tool for doing this but had minimal success with it. Today, I found an &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;ArcGIS 10 Add-In&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; that is suppose to do the same thing. In my experiments (sample size n=1) it worked perfectly. If you need this sort of functionality, I would recommend trying out this Add-In first, if that fails go the sde command line route. Use the direct SQL method at your own risk!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Domain Sorter Add-In Version 1.1</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2012-03-21-domain-sorter-add-in-version-1-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Mar 2012 18:19:03 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2012-03-21-domain-sorter-add-in-version-1-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Almost &lt;a href=&#34;http://maprantala.com/2011/05/03/sorting-a-coded-value-domain-add-in-arcgis-10/&#34;&gt;a year ago&lt;/a&gt;, I updated ERSI’s &lt;a href=&#34;http://edndoc.esri.com/arcobjects/9.2/CPP_VB6_VBA_VCPP_Doc/COM_Samples_Docs/Geodatabase/Schema_Creation_and_Management/Sort_a_domain/e826c5a8-9740-4f0b-86b6-d3b834735574.htm&#34;&gt;Domain Sort code for VB 6&lt;/a&gt; to work with ArcGIS 10. Recently, I had a comment that this Add-In caused ArcCatalog to explode if you had an open OLE connection. When I tested it, it turned out the reports were accurate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/arccatalog.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got around to adding in a Try-Catch around the offending chunk of code &amp;amp; it is now better than ever. You can download just the &lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.dropbox.com/u/22241283/NodeDangles/DomainSorter.esriAddIn&#34;&gt;Add-In&lt;/a&gt; or the &lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.dropbox.com/u/22241283/NodeDangles/20120321_DomainSort.zip&#34;&gt;Add-In with source code&lt;/a&gt; or get it from &lt;a href=&#34;http://resources.arcgis.com/gallery/file/arcobjects-net-api/details?entryID=B5E1BB12-1422-2418-34B7-D3A6908560FA&#34;&gt;ESRI’s ArcGIS Resource Center&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ArcGIS Add-In Custom Mouse Cursor</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2011-07-19-arcgis-add-in-custom-mouse-cursor/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jul 2011 20:47:03 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2011-07-19-arcgis-add-in-custom-mouse-cursor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was working on a project and wanted my own custom mouse cursor and did not easily find a way to make your own in ESRI’s instructions.  But, once you know how to do it, it is pretty easy.  In Visual Studio, Add a New Item:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i2.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/07/addresource.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add a Cursor File:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/07/selectcursor.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can edit your cursor with the editor program in Visual Studio.  Once you satisfied with how it looks, make sure that the Build Action on the cursor is “Embedded Resource”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i0.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/07/embedded.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then you can set your cursor with two lines of code. Not that my cursor is in my QDI.QdiAddIn Namespace:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Renaming Raster Dataset and arcpy.Exists()</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2011-05-03-renaming-raster-dataset-and-arcpy-exists/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2011 09:33:48 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2011-05-03-renaming-raster-dataset-and-arcpy-exists/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Discovered something today. I was working on an arcpy script that copies a raster dataset from a file geodatabase into a Postgres SDE geodatabase and then does some boring routine tasks–building stats, creating a mosaic dataset, adding the raster to the mosaic dataset and making a couple referenced mosaic datasets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It sometimes has trouble with the initial step of uploading the raster because of the sheer size of if (1m elevation raster for counties) and it failed today on one. It failed today so I used the ArcCatalog GUI to copy the raster and renamed it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then proceeded to run launch my script. Before each step, I use &lt;a href=&#34;http://help.arcgis.com/en/arcgisdesktop/10.0/help/index.html#/Exists/000v00000021000000/&#34;&gt;arcpy.Exists&lt;/a&gt;() extensively to check to see if various items exist before I attempt to create them. It was continuously reporting that my raster set did not exist even though I could see it in ArcCatalog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I realized that I needed to close ArcCatalog before arcpy recognized the fact I had renamed something. To note, I was running arcpy from a separate PythonWin window, not from the ArcCatalog session I had renamed the raster dataset with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I closed ArcCatalog, arcpy recognized the renaming and life was good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m also suspicious now about a problem I often have running statistics on my rasters.  The ArcTool reports no errors when I create them but for some reason the raster does not show that it has statistics afterwards.  I normally have multiple ArcApplication sessions open and now suspect that perhaps this problem is due to sessions not letting go of the connection.  Stay tuned for further developments on this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sorting a Coded-Value Domain Add-In (ArcGIS 10)</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2011-05-03-sorting-a-coded-value-domain-add-in-arcgis-10/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2011 03:33:01 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2011-05-03-sorting-a-coded-value-domain-add-in-arcgis-10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am working on an data-entry application to edit feature classes that contain several coded-value-domains. The problem with some of the domains, however, is that some entries have been added after the initial creation.  So the first 25 entries are in alphabetical order and there are some stragglers at the end that are in the order they were appended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can be confusing for users–they go to select “Milli Vanilli” and look between “Madonna” and “Motley Crue” but can not find their favorite band there–they have to go to the end of the list to find their selection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past, I have gone through the tedious process of exporting the domain to a table, sorting the table, removing the domain from the necessary field(s), deleting the domain, re-importing the table back in a new domain and finally re-applying the domain to the necessary field(s). Let’s just say I didn’t do this until someone asked a few times and I didn’t have anything more exciting–like a root canal–I could busy myself with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this new application contains more domains than any of other datasets so it was time to find a better solution. ESRI does have a &lt;a href=&#34;http://edndoc.esri.com/arcobjects/9.2/CPP_VB6_VBA_VCPP_Doc/COM_Samples_Docs/Geodatabase/Schema_Creation_and_Management/Sort_a_domain/e826c5a8-9740-4f0b-86b6-d3b834735574.htm&#34;&gt;Domain Sort&lt;/a&gt; Developer Sample.  It, however, did &lt;a href=&#34;http://edndoc.esri.com/arcobjects/9.2/CPP_VB6_VBA_VCPP_Doc/COM_Samples_Docs/Geodatabase/Schema_Creation_and_Management/Sort_a_domain/e826c5a8-9740-4f0b-86b6-d3b834735574.htm&#34;&gt;not play nice&lt;/a&gt; with ArcGIS 10.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I went ahead and update it from VB 6 to VB.Net/ArcObjects 10.  I made an &lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.dropbox.com/u/22241283/NodeDangles/DomainSorter.esriAddIn&#34;&gt;Add-In&lt;/a&gt; that can be installed by downloading the .esriaddin file and double-clicking on it.  The &lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.dropbox.com/u/22241283/NodeDangles/20120321_DomainSort.zip&#34;&gt;source code&lt;/a&gt; is also available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will add an ArcCatalog Toolbar that can be added by going to Customize-Toolbars-Domain Sorter Toolbar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i2.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/ds_1.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will add a toolbar with one button.  The button enables whenever you select a geodatabase with at least one coded-value domain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i2.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/ds_2.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This brings up a Windows form that lets you sort any domain by either the code or description, ascending or descending.  Once you hit “OK” it re-sorts your domain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/04/ds_3.png&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only problem I have had is that only the owner of a domain is allowed to edit it on an SDE geodatabase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But other than that, the button allows you to easily keep your domains sorted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://edndoc.esri.com/arcobjects/9.2/CPP_VB6_VBA_VCPP_Doc/COM_Samples_Docs/Geodatabase/Schema_Creation_and_Management/Sort_a_domain/e826c5a8-9740-4f0b-86b6-d3b834735574.htm&#34;&gt;http://edndoc.esri.com/arcobjects/9.2/CPP_VB6_VBA_VCPP_Doc/COM_Samples_Docs/Geodatabase/Schema_Creation_and_Management/Sort_a_domain/e826c5a8-9740-4f0b-86b6-d3b834735574.htm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Instantiating Add-In Objects at Load Time</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2011-03-02-instantiating-add-in-objects-at-load-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 15:18:14 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2011-03-02-instantiating-add-in-objects-at-load-time/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In migrating a toolbar consisting of a button and a couple of tools for use in ArcMap 10, I decided to take advantage of the ease of deployment enabled by add-ins which was introduced in 10.0.  So far, I’m loving the functionality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing, however, that I have to figure out is that the controls are not instantiated until they are clicked on.  One of the results is that the controls, by default, are enabled.  This is not the functionality I wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found the solution in ESRI’s topic, &lt;a href=&#34;http://help.arcgis.com/en/sdk/10.0/arcobjects_net/conceptualhelp/index.html#/Advanced_add_in_concepts/0001000004n7000000/&#34;&gt;Advanced add-in concepts (ArcObjects .NET 10 SDK)&lt;/a&gt; in the Delayed loading section:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The verbiage, “setting the onDemand Extensible Markup Language (XML) attribute to false” was a bit non-specific to me.  I guessed right, however, that they were referring to the control definiton in the Command section of Config.esriaddinx.  In the example below, I set the onDemand attribute to false by adding the  ‘onDemand=”false”‘ tag and the control did, in fact, get instantiated at load time, giving me the ability to disable it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Walkthrough: Building custom UI elements using add-ins (ArcObjects .NET 10 SDK)</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2011-02-15-walkthrough-building-custom-ui-elements-using-add-ins-arcobjects-net-10-sdk/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2011 17:05:55 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2011-02-15-walkthrough-building-custom-ui-elements-using-add-ins-arcobjects-net-10-sdk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was working my way through this ESRI &lt;a href=&#34;http://help.arcgis.com/en/sdk/10.0/arcobjects_net/conceptualhelp/index.html#//0001000001ms000000&#34;&gt;Walkthrough: Building custom UI elements using add-ins (ArcObjects .NET 10 SDK)&lt;/a&gt;.  And came across a couple minor errors that I had to correct during the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, while implementing the OnClick() code for ZoomToLayer.vb, Visual Studio gave me a “Name ‘ArcMap’ is not declared.” error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/arcmapnotdeclared.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the walk-through, they mention that the ArcMap method of your class.  For me, however, it appeared under the .My method.  Not sure if this is something specific to my set-up or, as I’m guessing, something that got changed after the first documentation was created and the final libraries published.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i0.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/objectbrowser.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fix is just adding  “My.” to the namespace in this line:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I added the code for AddGraphics.vb, I got 8 errors.  There was essentially two errors, repeated four times.  I took a screen shot after fixing the first error pair:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://i2.wp.com/maprantala.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/errorlist.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fixes in this case was also to use the complete name space path.  Examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Change this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And change this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, the walk-through is very well done, just a couple minor tweaks.  I am now working my way through modifying an existing solution–one that included seven projects–to see if I can create an ArcGIS 10 Add-In.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Launching a Python script with parameters&amp;#8211;3 methods.</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2010-12-13-launching-a-python-script-with-parameters-3-methods/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2010 14:56:43 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2010-12-13-launching-a-python-script-with-parameters-3-methods/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Since I use python for different tasks, I launch python scripts a variety of ways. Depending on what I am doing, a single script may need to accept parameters from either:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Passed in from an ArcGIS Toolbox Tool.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Re-occurring default value.  Often used in scheduled processes, a nightly backup, for example.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A temporary set of values used in an interactive, debugging session.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I often do is make the parameter interpretation flexible to meet my needs.  The sample below shows how I do this.  The logic first checks to see if the correct number of parameters were used to launch the script (i.e. if it is called by an Arc Toolbox tool), where the files for the default files exist or if the debug values are valid, including checking the current date against a hard-coded date variable.  Juggling the conditional structure would allow you to prioritize the options differently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am also using Tkinter to display an interactive dialog if none of the three conditions are successfully met.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Example of how to add controls in data grid VB.NET</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2010-12-09-example-of-how-to-add-controls-in-data-grid-vb-net/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Dec 2010 17:15:35 -0600</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2010-12-09-example-of-how-to-add-controls-in-data-grid-vb-net/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been working on some data entry forms that utilize a DataGrid.  Using a PostGres Geodatabase that had domains set on several fields, I could not directly bind to the controls on my dialog.  So I am going the round-about way of populating my own comboboxes with valid names and displaying within the DataGrid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having not done this previously, I found this example: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eggheadcafe.com/community/aspnet/14/22477/example-of-how-to-add-controls-in-data-grid.aspx&#34;&gt;Example of how to add controls in data grid VB.NET&lt;/a&gt; very useful and just wanted to point it out to anyone.  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.syncfusion.com/FAQ/windowsforms/faq_c44c.aspx#q1015q&#34;&gt;George Shephard’s Windows Forms FAQ&lt;/a&gt; also had several useful tips.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I has a problem with the masked textboxs I added to the Datagrid, they required users to click once to get focus and a second to start editing.  After much googling, I found used some information from &lt;a href=&#34;http://social.msdn.microsoft.com/Forums/en-US/vbgeneral/thread/8d3c1f98-9501-4902-b81b-82f6bbd4f3e5/&#34;&gt;MSDN&lt;/a&gt; that allowed me to find a work-around.  In my Mousedown event, I included this snippet (QdiControl is the control for the specific cell that the HitTestInfo says the mousedown hit):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peace.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ArcBruTile</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2010-09-09-arcbrutile/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Sep 2010 14:38:46 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2010-09-09-arcbrutile/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Stumbled across &lt;a href=&#34;http://arcbrutile.codeplex.com/&#34;&gt;ArcBruTile&lt;/a&gt;, an ArcMap application that allows you to display map tile services–such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.openstreetmap.org/&#34;&gt;OpenStreetMap&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://maps.google.com/&#34;&gt;Google Maps&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bing.com/maps/&#34;&gt;Bing&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.spatialcloud.com/&#34;&gt;Spatial Cloud&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.osgeo.org/wiki/Tile_Map_Service_Specification&#34;&gt;Tile Map Service&lt;/a&gt; (TMS)–in your ArcMap documents.   It works pretty well from my preliminary testing of it.   I have found that at times that the graphical tiles are distorted but I am guessing it is because they are optimized for display in a specific projection, at specific scales and, in ArcMap, you can use any projection/scale combination you want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a free, open-source project that is still in Beta but definitely an application I plan to keep an eye on.  As with any open-source project, the cool thing is the code is available for you to look at, learn from, and hopefully contribute to.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
