<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>North Dakota on Node Dangles</title>
    <link>https://maprantala.com/tags/north-dakota/</link>
    <description>Recent content in North Dakota on Node Dangles</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Jul 2010 13:53:28 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://maprantala.com/tags/north-dakota/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>North Dakota Geological Survey</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/2010/07/12/north-dakota-geological-survey/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jul 2010 13:53:28 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/2010/07/12/north-dakota-geological-survey/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Took a quick look at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dmr.nd.gov/ndgs/&#34;&gt;North Dakota Geological Survey’s website&lt;/a&gt; for GIS data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only data I found served directly from their website was &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dmr.nd.gov/ndgs/surfacegeo/surfacemapsnew.asp&#34;&gt;surface geology map&lt;/a&gt; .pdfs for some 24k and 100k maps.  Also available is a search for &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dmr.nd.gov/oilgas/findwellsvw.asp&#34;&gt;Oil &amp;amp; Gas wells&lt;/a&gt; although I did not see the data was downloadable.  Some other &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dmr.nd.gov/ndgs/Publication_List/contentsnew.asp&#34;&gt;publications&lt;/a&gt; have .pdfs that can be downloaded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://web.apps.state.nd.us/imf/sites/hubexplorer/jsp/index.jsp&#34;&gt;North Dakota Hub Explorer&lt;/a&gt; serves as the state’s official data portal including for GIS data.  The downloadable data includes bedrock geology, surface geology, and contours.  Interestingly, the site allows you to choose from 7 different coordinate systems and 27 different file formats including several AutoCad, ESRI, MapInfo, and KML.  The data I looked at had more attribution than the bare minimum shown on a hard-copy map.  Bedrock data, for example, had additional lithology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though I appeared to be getting a &lt;em&gt;Request is complex&lt;/em&gt; error message, their system functioned very well, you step your way through a few selections and a few minutes later you receive an email providing a link to start a download of your compressed data.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
