<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>point to line segment on Node Dangles</title>
    <link>https://maprantala.com/tags/point-to-line-segment/</link>
    <description>Recent content in point to line segment on Node Dangles</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 16 May 2010 17:14:23 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://maprantala.com/tags/point-to-line-segment/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Measuring distance from a point to a line segment in Python.</title>
      <link>https://maprantala.com/posts/2010-05-16-measuring-distance-from-a-point-to-a-line-segment/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 May 2010 17:14:23 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://maprantala.com/posts/2010-05-16-measuring-distance-from-a-point-to-a-line-segment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently had the need to calculate the distance from a point (address point) to a polyline (street segment) and wanted to avoid using any additional libraries because it was being done for an external client. Ok, I actually used arcgisscripting for reading the data but that lacked, from what I could tell, the fine-detail granularity of measuring distance between individual geometries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But since the only spatial operations I needed were to measure the distance between two points and the distance between a point and polyline, I decided to just do it via brute force. The datasets being processed were not huge so it made this feasible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Measuring point-to-point distance was easy enough. And while I knew I could work through the details of measuring the distance between a point and polyline, I decided NOT to re-invent the wheel if I did not have to. Google did not come up with any direct answers but I did come across this &lt;a href=&#34;http://local.wasp.uwa.edu.au/%7Epbourke/geometry/pointline/&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&#34;http://local.wasp.uwa.edu.au/%7Epbourke/&#34; title=&#34;Paul Bourke&#34;&gt;Paul Bourke&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://wasp.uwa.edu.au/&#34;&gt;University of Western Australia&lt;/a&gt; about measuring the distance between a point and a line segment. A polyline is just a series of line segments so I used it as the basis of my measurement–I just loop through all the consecutive vertice pairs, using the minimum distance found.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul did not have a python implementation included, so I went ahead and created my own from his information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
